Johanna Beyer

Curriculum Vitae

I am a researcher in the field of visual computing, with a focus on scalable techniques for high-throughput data visualization and visual methods for large-scale data analysis. I am also interested in the combination of abstract information visualization with scientific visualization for novel domain-specific applications.

Education

- 2004–2009 **Ph.D. in Computer Science**, Vienna University of Technology, Austria.

 Dissertation: GPU-based Multi-Volume Rendering of Complex Data in Neuroscience and Neurosurgery.

 Ph.D. committee: Prof. Dr. Eduard Gröller, Prof. Dr. Hanspeter Pfister.
- 2000–2004 **Dipl. Ing. (FH) in Medical Software Engineering**, Upper Austrian University of Applied Science, Austria.

Research Experience

- 2016-now Research Associate, Visual Computing Group, Harvard University, USA.
- 2013–2016 Postdoctoral Fellow, Visual Computing Group, Harvard University, USA.
 - 2013 **Visiting Research Fellow**, *Institute of Computer Graphics and Algorithms, Vienna University of Technology*, Austria.
- 2010–2013 **Postdoctoral Fellow**, Geometric Modeling and Scientific Visualization Research Center, King Abdullah University of Science and Technology (KAUST), Saudi Arabia.
 - 2009 Visiting Research Fellow, Initiative on Innovative Computing, Harvard University, USA.
- 2008–2010 Researcher, Visualization Group, VRVis Research Center, Austria.
- 2004–2008 Junior Researcher, Medical Visualization Group, VRVis Research Center, Austria.

Teaching Experience

Classroom Teaching

- 2017 Lecturer, Visualization, 70 undergraduate and graduate students. Harvard University...
- 2015-2016 **Head Teaching Fellow**, *Visualization*, 240 undergraduate and online students. Harvard University.
- 2013–2014 **Senior Teaching Fellow**, *Visualization*, Harvard University.
 - 2014 **Senior Teaching Fellow**, *Systems Development for Computational Science*, 70 graduate and online students. Harvard University.
 - 2013 **Senior Teaching Fellow**, *Data Science*, 400 undergraduate, graduate and online students. Harvard University.
- 2010–2012 **Teaching Fellow**, Scientific Visualization, KAUST.
- 2010–2012 **Teaching Fellow**, GPU and GPGPU Programming, KAUST.

Student Co-Supervision and Mentoring

2015—now Leader of the visualization subgroup of Prof. Pfister's lab, including student mentoring, Harvard University.

- 2013-now Supervision of PhD students and Master's theses, Harvard University.
- 2010–2012 Supervision of Master's theses and directed research, King Abdullah University of Science and Technology.
- 2009–2010 Supervision of Master's theses and directed research, VRVis Research Center.

Academic Activities

Committees Program Committee IEEE SciVis 2014-2015, 2017.

Program Committee EuroVis 2014, 2016.

Posters Chair IEEE LDAV 2015.

Program Committee IEEE LDAV 2014, 2015, 2017.

Program Committee EuroVis Short Papers 2012-2014, 2017.

Conference IEEE Visualization Conference; ACM Siggraph; ACM Siggraph Asia; SC International Con-Reviewing ference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage and Analysis; ACM Chi; Eurographics Conference on Visualization; IEEE Pacific Visualization Symposium; IEEE/EG International Symposium on Volume and Point-Based Graphics; Eurographics Symposium on Parallel Graphics and Visualization; IEEE Symposium on Large-Scale Data Analysis and Visualization; International Conference in Central Europe on Computer Graphics, Visualization and Computer Vision; Eurographics Workshop on Visual Computing for Biology and Medicine; Central European Seminar on Computer Graphics.

Journal IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics; IEEE Computer Graphics and Reviewing Applications; Computer Graphics Forum; The Visual Computer; Computer Assisted Radiology and Surgery; Information Visualization; Computers in Biology and Medicine; Neuroinformatics.

Grants and Grant Writing Experience

- 2016-2017 Administrating:, CCF collaborative research project Harvard University, KAUST Visual Computing Center, with Hanspeter Pfister and Markus Hadwiger.
- 2013-2015 Administrating: NSF OIA-1125087, with Hanspeter Pfister.
- 2013-2015 Administrating: Harvard Cuda Center of Excellence, with Hanspeter Pfister.
 - 2015 Assisting: KAUST CCF Grant Proposal, with Markus Hadwiger.
 - 2011 Sabic Postdoctoral Fellowship, post-doctoral funding.
 - 2008 Marshall Plan Scholarship, partial doctoral funding.
 - 2008 Assisting: WWTF ICT08-040, with Markus Hadwiger.

Publications – Journal and Reviewed Conference Publications

- 2017 H. Mohammed, A. K. Al-Awami, J. Beyer, C. Corrado Cali, P. Magistretti, H. Pfister, and M. Hadwiger. Abstractocyte: A Visual Tool for Exploring Nanoscale Astroglial Cells. IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics, (Proc. of IEEE SciVis 2017), to appear.
- 2017 M. Hadwiger, A. K. Al-Awami, J. Beyer, M. Agos, and H. Pfister. SparseLeap: Efficient Empty Space Skipping for Large-Scale Volume Rendering. IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics, (Proc. of IEEE SciVis 2017), to appear.
- 2015 A. K. Al-Awami, J. Beyer, D. Haehn, N. Kasthuri, J. W. Lichtman, H. Pfister, and M. Hadwiger. NeuroBlocks - Visual Tracking of Segmentation and Proofreading for Large Connectomics Projects. IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics, (Proc. of IEEE SciVis 2015).
- 2015 J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, and H. Pfister. State-of-the-Art in GPU-Based Large-Scale Volume Visualization. Computer Graphics Forum.

- 2014 A. K. Al-Awami, J. Beyer, H. Strobelt, N. Kasthuri, J. W. Lichtman, H. Pfister, and M. Hadwiger. NeuroLines: A Subway Map Metaphor for Visualizing Nanoscale Neuronal Connectivity. *IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics, (Proc. of IEEE InfoVis 2014)*.
- 2014 D. Haehn, S. Knowles-Barley, M. Roberts, J. Beyer, N. Kasthuri, J. W. Lichtman, and H. Pfister. Design and Evaluation of Interactive Proofreading Tools for Connectomics. *IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics, (Proc. of IEEE SciVis 2014)*.
- 2013 J. Beyer, A. K. Al-Awami, N. Kasthuri, J. W. Lichtman, H. Pfister, and M. Hadwiger. onnectomeExplorer: Query-Guided Visual Analysis of Large Volumetric Neuroscience Data. *IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics, (Proc. of IEEE SciVis 2013).*
- 2013 J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, A. Al-Awami, W.-K. Jeong, N. Kasthuri, J. W. Lichtman, and H. Pfister. Exploring the Connectome - Petascale Volume Visualization of Microscopy Data Streams. *IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications*.
- 2012 M. Hadwiger, R. Sicat, J. Beyer, J. Krüger, and T. Möller. Sparse PDF Maps for Non-Linear Multi-Resolution Image Operations. ACM Transactions on Graphics (Proc. of SIGGRAPH Asia 2012).
- 2012 M. Hadwiger, J. Beyer, W.-K. Jeong, and H. Pfister. nteractive Volume Exploration of Petascale Microscopy Data Streams Using a Visualization-Driven Virtual Memory Approach. *IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. of IEEE SciVis 2012).*
- 2011 T. Hoellt, J. Beyer, F. Gschwantner, P. Muigg, H. Doleisch, G. Heinemann, and M. Hadwiger. Interactive Seismic Interpretation with Piecewise Global Energy Minimization. *Proc. of IEEE Pacific Visualization*.
- 2010 W.-K. Jeong, J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, R. Blue, C. Law, A. Vasquez, C. Reid, J. Lichtman, and H. Pfister. SSECRETT and NeuroTrace: Interactive Visualization and Analysis Tools for Large-Scale Neuroscience Datasets. *IEEE Computer Graphics and Applications*.
- 2009 W.-K. Jeong, J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, A. Vasquez, H. Pfister, and R. Whitaker. Scalable and Interactive Segmentation and Visualization of Neural Processes in EM Datasets. *IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. of IEEE Visualization 2009)*.
- 2008 J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, T. Möller, and L. Fritz. Smooth Mixed-Resolution GPU Volume Rendering. *Proc. of IEEE International Symposium on Volume and Point-Based Graphics* 2008.
- 2007 J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, S. Wolfsberger, and K. Bühler. High-Quality Multimodal Volume Rendering for Preoperative Planning of Neurosurgical Interventions. *IEEE Trans. on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. of IEEE Visualization 2007).*
- 2007 J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, S. Wolfsberger, C. Rezk-Salama, and K. Bühler. Segmentierungsfreie Visualisierung des Gehirns für Direktes Volume Rendering. *Proc. of Bildverarbeitung für die Medizin 2007.*
- 2007 J. Beyer, C. Langer, L. Fritz, M. Hadwiger, S. Wolfsberger, and K. Bühler. Interactive Diffusion Based Smoothing and Segmentation of Volumetric Datasets on Graphics Hardware. *Methods of Information in Medicine*.

Publications – Book Chapters

2011 W.-K. Jeong, H. Pfister, J. Beyer, and M. Hadwiger. GPU-accelerated Brain Connectivity Reconstruction and Visualization in Large-Scale Electron Micrographs. *GPU Computing Gems, Vol 1.*

Publications - Technical Sketches, Talks and Posters

- 2017 H. Mohammed, A. K. Al-Awami, J. Beyer, C. Corrado Cali, P. Magistretti, H. Pfister, and M. Hadwiger. Abstractocyte: A Visual Tool for Exploring Nanoscale Astroglial Cell Morphology. *Poster at IEEE Pacific Visualization (PacificVis)*.
- 2016 J. Beyer, H. Strobelt, M. Oppermann, L. Deslauriers, and H. Pfister. Teaching Visualization for Large and Diverse Classes on Campus and Online. *Pedagogy of Data Visualization Workshop*.
- 2014 A. K. Al-Awami, J. Beyer, H. Strobelt, N. Kasthuri, J. W. Lichtman, H. Pfister, M. Hadwiger. NeuroLines A Subway Map Metaphor for Visualizing Nanoscale Neuronal Connectivity. *Poster at 4th Symposium on Biological Data Visualization (BioVis)*.
- 2011 J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, W. Jeong, H. Pfister, J. Lichtmann, and C. Reid. Demand-Driven Volume Rendering of Terascale EM Data. *SIGGRAPH 2011 Talks*.
- 2011 J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, W. Jeong, H. Pfister. Distributed Terascale Volume Visualization Using a Shared Virtual Memory Space. *IEEE Symposium on Large-Scale Data Analysis and Visualization (LDAV)*.
- 2010 J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, W. Jeong, H. Pfister, J. Lichtmann, and C. Reid. Distributed Multi-Level Out-of-Core Volume Rendering. *Poster at NVIDIA GPU Technology Conference (NVIDIA Research Summit)*.

Publications – Courses

- 2014 J. Beyer, M. Hadwiger, H. Pfister. A Survey of GPU-Based Large-Scale Volume Visualization. *Eurographics Conference on Visualization (EuroVis) - State of The Art Reports.*
- 2013 M. Hadwiger, J. Krüger, J. Beyer, S. Bruckner. GPU-Based Large-Scale Visualization. SIGGRAPH Asia.

Invited Talks and Guest Lectures

- 2017 Guest lecture: Visualizing Spatial Data: Volumes and Flow. COMPSCI 205: Computing Foundations for Computational Science. Harvard University.
- 2016 Visualization for Connectomics. Immersive Approaches to Biological Data Visualization. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory.
- 2015 Visualization for Connectomics. Data Visualization Meeting. Broad Institute.
- 2015 Data Visualization and Visual Computing for Life Sciences. Visual Computing Center, King Abdullah University of Science and Technology.
- 2014 NeuroLines: A Subway Map Metaphor for Visualizing Nanoscale Neuronal Connectivity. CSAIL, Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
- 2012 Interactive Volume Exploration of Petascale Microscopy Data. Visual Computing Group, Harvard University.
- 2012 Petascale Visualization for Neuroscience. Workshop on Computational Biomedicine and Geophysics, Salt Lake City.
- 2011 Petascale Visualization for Neuroscience. Argonne National Labs.
- 2006 *High-Quality Real-Time Visualization of Medical Data*. European Workshop on basic techniques of microsurgery and cerebral revascularization.

Conference Presentations

2014 A Survey of GPU-Based Large-Scale Visualization. EuroVis.

- 2013 Course on GPU-Based Large-Scale Visualization. ACM Siggraph Asia.
- 2013 ConnectomeExplorer: Query-Guided Visual Analysis of Large Volumetric Neuroscience Data. IEEE SciVis.
- 2013 Interactive Non-Linear Image Operations on Gigapixel Images. NVIDIA GPU Technology Conference.
- 2012 Terascale Volume Visualization in Neuroscience. NVIDIA GPU Technology Conference.
- 2011 Demand-Driven Volume Rendering of Terascale EM Data. ACM Siggraph.
- 2009 Scalable and Interactive Segmentation and Visualization of Neural Processes. IEEE SciVis.
- 2008 Smooth Mixed-Resolution GPU Volume Rendering. IEEE Volume and Point-based Graphics.
- 2007 High-Quality Multimodal Volume Rendering for Preoperative Planning of Neurosurgical Interventions. IEEE Visualization.

Awards

- 2014 Best Paper Honorable Mention, IEEE InfoVis Conference.
- 2014 Best Poster, BioVis.
- 2012 Best Paper Honorable Mention, IEEE SciVis Conference.
- 2008 Medvis Award (Karl-Heinz-Höhne-Preis), second place.
- 2007 Best Applications Paper Award, IEEE Visualization Conference.
- 2011 Best Student Project Award, Upper Austrian University of Applied Sciences.